Today's דף daf is ל"ו Lamed Vav to ל"ז. Lamed Zayin. We
start on חוץ מן היין chutz min hayayin on ל"ה עמוד ב'
Lamed Hey Amud Bet about ten lines before the lines get wide,
the two dots. Okay, so the משנה Mishnah says that everything that
comes from the fruit gets a בורא פרי העץ Borei Pri Ha'etz
except wine which gets בורא פרי הגפן, Borei Pri Hagafen, assuming by
the way that even when something transforms it retains its ברכה bracha
because were it not that wine were special it seems like it
would have gotten a בורא פרי העץ. Borei Pri Ha'etz. So we'll
talk about that later, like just think for a minute do we
make בורא פרי העץ Borei Pri Ha'etz on apple juice, on orange
juice, and so on? Okay, but anyway wine doesn't get a בורא
פרי העץ, Borei Pri Ha'etz, wine gets a בורא פרי הגפן. Borei
Pri Hagafen. So let's see why. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: מאי שנא מיין, mai shna mayayin, why is wine different? Why
is it special that it gets its own ברכה? bracha? אילימא משום
דאשתני לעילויה, ilema mishum de'ishtani le'iluya, if it's because it changed to
a better state, wine is better than
grapes, so and אשתני לברכה, ishtani l'vracha, it gets a different ברכה,
bracha, it gets a special ברכה bracha for it. והרי שמן, ve'harei
shemen, how about oil? דאשתני לעילויה, de'ishtani le'iluya, olive oil is more
valuable than
olives and ולא אשתני לברכה, velo ishtani l'vracha, it doesn't, olive oil
doesn't get a special ברכה. bracha. דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, de'amar
Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, because רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said in the
name of שמואל, Shmuel, וכן אמר רב יצחק אמר רב יוחנן, vechein
amar Rav Yitzchak amar Rav Yochanan, שמן זית מברכין עליו בורא פרי
העץ, shemen zayis mevorchin alav borei pri ha'etz, that for olive oil
you make a ברכה bracha of בורא פרי העץ. Borei Pri Ha'etz.
When you drink it? Well, we'll talk about that. We make בורא
פרי העץ, Borei Pri Ha'etz, and we'll discuss in a minute the
immediate reaction that Michael just had which is that if normally you
don't eat something directly, you only dip something in it or other
things like that, do you even give it its own ברכה? bracha?
Do you give it the primary ברכה bracha and so on? But
regardless it's certainly clear that nobody ever suggested that you make a
special ברכה bracha by olive oil that's not of the normal ברכות.
brachos. So why is it different than wine? Of course part of
the answer could be because nobody eats olive oil directly, but let's
keep on going, see what the גמרא Gemara says. So אמרי, amri,
so the גמרא Gemara says you can say התם משום דלא אפשר,
hatam mishum delo efshar, that it's not possible to make a special
ברכה bracha by olive oil. What do you mean? היכי נברך, heichi
nevarech, what type of, what do you want to say, what ברכה
bracha do you want? נברך בורא פרי הזית, nevarech Borei Pri Hazayis,
if you'd like בורא פרי הגפן, Borei Pri Hagafen, you want to
say בורא פרי הזית, Borei Pri Hazayis, the fruit of the olive
tree? So פירא גופיה זית איקרי, pira gufa zayis ikri, that won't
work because זית zayis is also the name of the olive, so
you can't say the fruit of the olive. And actually you could
if fruit meant the thing that's derived from the olive which is
the olive oil, but again then that's not as we said before
that's not something that God directly made, that's something that came through
also the human process. So even when we make a special ברכה
bracha on wine we still emphasize sort of the natural state of
the fruit of the vine which literally really is the grape, except
because we emphasize the vine somehow that alludes to the idea that
this is something special, this has been turned into wine. So it's
interesting to just note that fact that nobody's suggesting that you're going
to make directly the ברכה bracha on God you created olive oil
because God didn't create olive oil, God created the olives and human
beings were part of the process of creating olive oil. So therefore
what should we make?
Without human beings there would still be, unless we have other natural
disasters, olive trees in this world and grapes that would be wild,
they wouldn't be cultivated, but that's still part of the natural world
without human intervention. Okay, so we could say God creates the fruit
of the trees, God creates the fruit of the vine, all those
are true. But when we're talking about the, if you were going
to make a ברכה, bracha, you know, בורא פרי הגפן, Borei Pri
Hagafen, בורא היין Borei Hayayin or בורא שמן זית, Borei Shemen Zayis,
God did not create oil, olive oil, God created the olives and
then human beings were part of the process of creating olive oil.
So right, so it's why by wine we don't say בורא היין,
Borei Hayayin, we say בורא פרי הגפן, Borei Pri Hagafen, which ultimately
refers to the fruit of the vine is still really the grapes.
If you think about it even the ברכה bracha we make on
wine literally is a ברכה bracha on grapes, but because it emphasizes
the vine and it's a little abstract, it doesn't say grapes, it
says the fruit of the vine, it could abstractly be extended to
include wine. But literally it's about what God has directly created which
is the fruit of the vine, the grapes. Okay, so therefore there's
never a suggestion we should make by olive oil a
ברכה bracha like בורא שמן זית. Borei Shemen Zayis. We have to
make a ברכה bracha that relates to directly what God created. So
if you want to make an analogous ברכה, bracha, the fruit of
the olive tree, which emphasizes the olive tree, it's a little abstract
so it could come from the idea fruit of could include also
the idea of oil. So the גמרא Gemara says that's a little
bit of a problem because the word זית zayis doesn't just mean
olive tree, it means olive. And the fruit of the olive, God
did not create the fruit of the olive. What's the fruit of
the olive? A, it's either not true or if you interpret the
word fruit abstractly it means what was produced by the olive which
is the olive oil, but God didn't create the olive oil that
was in partnership with human beings. Okay, so the basic principle being
that the ברכה bracha has to be something be able to mean
literally what God directly created but also incorporate this idea of wine,
oil and so on. So it's possible to do by בורא פרי
הגפן, Borei Pri Hagafen, it's not possible just in terms of the
text is what the גמרא Gemara is saying right now to do
by the olive oil.
בורא פרי הכרם Borei Pri Hakarem
you could have said בורא פרי הכרם Borei Pri Hakarem you could
have said that by instead of
גפן. gefen. כרם זית איקרי, kerem zayit ikrei, כרם לא איקרי, kerem
lo ikrei, סתם כרם. stam kerem. You could have said כרם זית,
kerem zayit, I guess, בורא פרי הכרם Bore pri hakerem as כרם
זית. kerem zayit. I suppose you could have said that. We'll see
what the גמרא, Gemara, how the גמרא Gemara continues. Yes, Dave.
Does anybody comment on the fact that both with regard to wine
making and bread making...
With regard to wine and...
Both with regard to wine making and bread making. Yes. Human beings,
the manufacturing process is actually moderating a natural process of fermentation.
Aha.
Interesting point. As opposed to oil where it's just extracting it, here
it's somehow continuing the process of it. But I don't know, but
oil, but grape juice would, I mean
grape juice left on its own will turn to something
else, whether it's vinegar or wine. Right, but that's once you've extracted
it. Grapes on themselves won't, you know?
I understand, you suggest that the partnership...
And yeast will, but right, but you're saying you're seeing it more
as like an active partnership, it's not just the extraction, it's some
continuing of the process.
Correct, as if the partnership continues.
Right, that's a very nice idea. Thank you. All right, so let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. So it says you can't say
בורא פרי הזית. Bore pri hazayit. פירא גופא זית איקרי. Peira gufa
zayit ikrei. That would mean the fruit of the olive and that's
not true, God didn't create that. So נברך עליה בורא פרי עץ
הזית, nivarech alei Bore pri etz hazayit, so don't want to say
כרם זית, kerem zayit, גמרא Gemara says עץ הזית. etz hazayit. Okay
fine, being more explicit, creating the fruit of the olive tree. So
you can't say that it's a textual problem. We could have figured,
we're smart enough, we could have figured out some appropriate text. Exactly.
Right. Literature's not the problem.
Exactly. אלא אמר מר זוטרא: Ela amar Mar Zutra: חמרא זיין, chamra
zayen, משחא לא זיין. mishcha lo zayen. Wine satiates or gives sustenance,
oil does not, which might mean people don't directly eat oil, which
doesn't seem like that's what it's saying. This text just says wine
fills you up, you know, oil makes you maybe... actually I had
one of my students once had this diet which is basically about
like you drink like a whole glass of oil straight in the
morning, then you feel like you don't want to eat the rest
of the day. But actually there was a diet like that. Anyway,
but the גמרא Gemara is saying that oil either you won't drink
enough of it or it just doesn't satiate you, fill you up
the same way wine does. So therefore it's not as important to
merit its own ברכה. beracha. So the גמרא Gemara says ומשחא לא
זיין, u'mishcha lo zayen, oil doesn't satisfy you? והתנן, Vehatnan, we learned
in the משנה: Mishnah: הנודר מן המזון, Ha-noder min hamazon, if somebody
takes a vow that they will not benefit, they will not get
any benefit from food, from מזון, mazon, things that provide sustenance. Okay,
I don't know how this person is going to live before they
get this vow annulled. So here's the only two things that you
would be able to
eat, which really מותר במים ובמלח. mutar bemayim u'bemelech. You can eat
water and salt, those are not considered מזון, mazon, food or sustenance.
Those you can drink, so you better get that vow annulled pretty
soon. Anyway,
the גמרא Gemara says רבינא בנביא אפיש דהאי: Ravina banvei apish de-hai:
מים ומלח הוא דלא איקרי מזון. Mayim u'melech hu delo ikrei mazon.
That suggests that wine, and water and salt are the only things
not called מזון. mazon. הא כל מילי איקרי מזון? Ha kol milei
ikrei mazon? This seems to be that everything else in the world
is called
מזון. mazon. נימא תהוי תיובתא דרב ושמואל? Neima tehei tiyuvta de-Rav u-Shmuel?
So when we in this סוגיא sugya by, you know, by נדרים,
Nedarim, we asked this question. So let this be a challenge to
רב ושמואל. Rav u-Shmuel. דאמרי, De-amri, because רב ושמואל Rav u-Shmuel say:
אין מברכין בורא מיני מזונות אלא בחמשת המינים בלבד. Ein mevorchin Bore
minei mezonot ela be-chameshet haminim bilvad. We only say בורא מיני מזונות
Bore minei mezonot by the five types of grain. And according to
this, we should, I don't know why it says רב ושמואל, Rav
u-Shmuel, it's clear you don't say מזונות mezonot on everything. And according
to this, everything is called מזון, mazon, so make a בורא מיני
מזונות Bore minei mezonot on everything under the sun? So the גמרא
Gemara says ואמר רב הונא: ve-amar Rav Huna: So here's how we
distinguished. באומר כל הזן עלי. Be-omer kol hazan alai. You didn't say
מזון mazon directly. מזון mazon directly is true, it's only things that
are real sort of filler, things like the five species of grain.
But when you say כל הזן, kol hazan, not something that has
its identity as מזון, mazon, but anything that is זן, zan, anything
that provides some type of sustenance, should be forbidden to me. So
there's a difference between being defined as a staple, as sustenance, or
something that provides sustenance. So when you said anything that provides sustenance,
that includes everything under the sun except water and salt. So now
we're seeing that everything is considered to provide sustenance. אלמא משחא זיין.
Alma mishcha zayen. So you see even olive oil provides some degree
of sustenance. אלא Ela says the גמרא Gemara fine, let's take it
one step further. חמרא סעיד, Chamra saad, wine not just provides sustenance
but it satiates. משחא לא סעיד, Mishcha lo saad, oil does not
satiate. So now the גמרא Gemara says ובחמרא מי סעיד, u'bechamra mi
saad, is it really true that wine satiates? והא רבא הוה שתי
חמרא כל מעלי יומא דפסחא. Veha Rava hava shati chamra kol amalyoma
de-pischa. רבא Rava would drink wine all ערב פסח. erev Pesach. Why?
כי היכי דנגרייה לליביה. Ki heichi denigrei libe. That it should sort
of literally drag his heart, meaning that it should increase, whet his
appetite. וניכול מצה טפי טובא. Ve-neichol matzah tefei tuva.
So and he could eat more מצה matzah because it should, he
wanted to really eat מצה matzah with a desire and an appetite,
so he drank wine that increased the appetite. So it's not that
it satiates, it increases the appetite. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
here's the difference. טובא גריר, Tuva garer, a lot of wine causes
a, whets the appetite. פורתא סעיד, Purta saad, a little wine satiates.
I don't know if anybody here is into wine if they can
tell me if that's true or not. I don't know. So now
the גמרא Gemara says, so ומי סעיד, umi sa'id, is that really
true that a little wine satiates? וכתיב, vichtiv, the verse says יין
ישמח לבב אנוש, yavin yismach levav enosh, wine will gladden the hearts
of men, ולחם לבב אנוש יסעד, v'lechem levav enosh yisad, and bread
will satiate the hearts of men. So you see bread satiates, wine
gladdens. So the גמרא Gemara says נהמא הוא דסעיד חמרא לא סעיד.
nama hu d'sa'id chamra lo sa'id. It's clear that bread satiates, wine
does not satiate. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, let's modify it,
let's restate it. אלא חמרא אית ביה תרתי. ela chamra it bay
tartei. No
no no, here's the way it works. Wine does two things: סעיד
ומשמח. sa'id u'mesame'ach.
It satiates and it makes you happy. So נהמא מסעד סעיד nama
misad sa'id bread just satiates you, לא משמח lo mesame'ach it does
not make you happy. So wine is like the cure-all, it both
fills you up and makes you happy. And anyway, that's what one
minute, that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying, let's finish this point
about why wine gets a special ברכה. bracha. So the גמרא Gemara
says אי הכי, ei hachi, if that's true, נברך עליה שלש ברכות.
nivareich alei shalosh brachot. So okay, if it's so great it fills
you up, say ברכת המזון birkat hamazon over wine. So the גמרא
Gemara says לא קבעי אינשי סעודתא עלויה. lo kavei inish sudata alei.
No, it might fill you up but you don't actually have a
meal of wine. Okay, it's true that when you drink wine it
fills you nicely but it does not, you don't make a meal
out of it.
So סעיד sa'id means, as you've been translating it, satiates, as opposed
to it establishes that you're having a meal.
Exactly, it does the biological function of filling you up, but it's
not the type of thing that קובע סעודה, kove'a seudah, put it
on
the table and people will say, oh great, what's for lunch?
Right.
A three-martini lunch, like a three-wine-glass lunch here. You know, I mean
I think an interesting parallel again, I'm not a big wine drinker
so I can't comment on that, but like people that are on
diets I think drink a lot of soda, diet soda because
the carbonation fills, gives you a greater sense of being full. But
you don't make a meal out of soda. So the גמרא Gemara
is saying somehow wine can fill you up but you're not making
a meal, so you don't do a ברכת המזון. birkat hamazon. So
אמר ליה רב נחמן בר יצחק לרבא. amar leh Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak le'Rava. So רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak says
to רבא, Rava, אי קבע ליה סעודתא מאי, i kava leh sudata
mai, let's say somebody actually says let's sit down for lunch, we're
just going to drink wine for lunch. So would you make a
ברכת המזון? birkat hamazon? Which gets into interesting questions about how much,
all right, subjectivity, how much various categories are going to be impacted
by, you know, context and by your subjective reality. So let's see
what the גמרא's Gemara response is. אמר ליה לכשיבא אליהו ויאמר הוי
קביעותא. amar leh l'chish yavo Eliyahu ve'yomar havi kviyuta.
If אליהו הנביא Eliyahu Hanavi were to come and tell me that
this is considered to be establishing a סעודה, seudah, then I'll
reconsider. השתא מיהא, Hashta mi'ha, but for the time being, בטלה דעתו
אצל כל אדם. batla deitei etzel kol adam. Nobody normal does that,
makes a meal out of wine, so your subjective reality cannot establish
it as a meal. Now that does raise an interesting question, the
גמרא Gemara says בטלה דעתו אצל כל אדם batla deitei etzel kol
adam when it's a very small percentage of the population that would
do something like this. But the גמרא Gemara also recognizes some circumstances
where a certain percentage of the population does it. Let's say 20%
of the population actually would make a meal out of wine. Would
those people do a ברכת המזון? birkat hamazon? So the גמרא Gemara
doesn't think that that's the case, that's the reality. But it still
leaves open the question of how much can certain subjective and contextual
aspects impact what ברכות brachot are being made. So here the גמרא
Gemara only rejects it because it's saying that's crazy, it's not a
normal thing to do. One more point, I will say that it's
clear that subjective aspects do sometimes impact first ברכה. bracha. When you
have a mixed dish, like sushi's a great example. What do you
say on sushi? בורא פרי האדמה? borei pri hadamah? Do you say
בורא מיני מזונות? borei minei mezonot? Do you say שהכל? shehakol? It's
got like all three. So somebody told me it's whatever mood I'm
in that day, like which thing I'm particularly interested in. So when
you have these mixed dishes, there's a question which is the עיקר
ikar which is the טפל tafel and there your subjective perspective does
make a big difference. That's interesting. Well we'll worry, we'll see about
it. But there are many cases where that does. But, but something
like whether it's considered a סעודה seudah for ברכת המזון, birkat hamazon,
you know that's not עיקר ikar and טפל, tafel, which is by
its very nature a subjective question. But whether is this מזונות, mezonot,
is this המוציא, hamotzi, is this something you do ברכת המזון, birkat
hamazon, that is a question whether you know subjective reality should have
any impact although
I was going to say in other words it's
so, if wine is the item around which they're exploring the parameters
or limits of ברכת המזון, birkat hamazon, for example, you would think
that if you had just a bowl of spaghetti, you should be
able to, you should have to say ברכת המזון birkat hamazon and
around that it's quite questioned.
Right. So that's exactly what I'm alluding to, that in the time
of the גמרא Gemara clearly the קביעת סעודה kvi'at seudah was on
פת. pat. Nowadays you know people could have meat and potatoes and
you know rice and vegetables and it'd be a wonderful meal and
nobody brought any bread to the table. So how much is there
a possibility when it is the normal thing to be קובע סעודה
kove'a seudah without bread, can that open the possibility of ברכת המזון?
birkat hamazon? For now we'll leave that open with Ephraim and Bobby.
I think it's kind of subjective to talk about bread as not
gladdening the heart. I think of my mother-in-law, may she rest in
peace, who her
issue
with weight was she could never resist bread. And I know other
people, if they just love she never drank wine, but she got
great pleasure. Right, right.
So I think there's an
interesting difference between so here's my question. Yes. The wine really affects
the mind, not the heart. Right. Mind, but bread, not so much.
Right. So heart is always used metaphorically anyway. I mean, the heart
is just a pump, so whatever heart in different cultures doesn't mean
emotions, doesn't mean intellect, and so on. But you're absolutely correct that
there's a difference between pleasure and joy. I mean some people get
joy from certain pleasures. Okay, but משמח mesameiach here does mean it
causes a sense of, you know, elation and inebriation. It's more than
just a pleasure. So there is that difference. But you're yeah, yes.
So I just want to tie this back. So then the reason
why we don't make a special ברכה bracha on this olive oil
is because it's not sustaining at all?
Well we'll see more about the olive oil. So let me get
back to that. So right now what the גמרא Gemara says is
what makes wine special more than olive oil is not just it's
an improvement, but it has all of these qualities. It fills you,
it gladdens you. Now of course, you know, we could have just
taken a step back and noticed that clearly, you know, culturally, wine
has a lot more weight than pretty much, you know, any of
these other things. So,
you know, other than the technical explanation of the גמרא Gemara satiates,
doesn't satiate, there's a cultural weight of wine is very powerful like
the גמרא Gemara said before אין אומרים שירה אלא על היין ein
omrim shira ela al hayayin and all those types of things could
have afforded it a special ברכה. bracha. Olive oil, the reason it
needs to sort of explain away olive oil is strange, because in
the end the גמרא Gemara said, well, it doesn't fill you up
so much and this and that, but the more direct answer is
that you don't eat olive oil directly, and therefore it doesn't merit
a special ברכה, bracha, and that we're actually going to turn to
right now. So let's see as we continue. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this.
גופא, gufa, let's look back at that earlier statement, we're about six
lines from the bottom. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל וכן אמר רב
יצחק אמר רבי יוחנן שמן זית מברכין עליו בורא פרי העץ. Amar
Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel vechein amar Rav Yitzchak amar Rabbi Yochanan shemen
zayit mevorchin alav borei pri ha'eitz. Olive oil you say בורא פרי
העץ. borei pri ha'eitz. היכי דמי? Heichi dami? Says, now the גמרא
Gemara says really? What's the case? אילימא דקא שתי ליה, Ilima deka
shati lei, if you drink it directly, אזיק מזק ליה, azeik mazeik
lei, that'll hurt you. That'll be, you know, deleterious to your health.
דתניא, Detanya, we taught in the ברייתא, braita, השותה שמן של תרומה,
hashoteh shemen shel truma, if somebody drinks תרומה truma oil, משלם את
הקרן ואינו משלם את החומש, meshaleim et hakeren ve'eino meshaleim et hachomesh,
then you pay only the principal, you don't add a fifth. הסך
שמן של תרומה, Hasach shemen shel truma, but if you put תרומה
truma oil on your body, you literally I guess anoint yourself, rub
it into your skin, משלם את הקרן ומשלם את החומש, meshaleim et
hakeren umeshaleim et hachomesh, you pay the principal plus a fifth. What
does this mean? The Torah says ואיש כי יאכל קדש בשגגה, ve'ish
ki yochal kodesh bishgaga, if a person eats something sanctified in error,
doesn't realize it's sanctified, and חז"ל Chazal tell us that that's not
referring to anything sanctified but specifically תרומה, truma, then it says you
pay it back and you add a fifth. So it's only when
you eat, when you derive a type of direct benefit of consumption.
So with oil, that would be considered rubbing it into your skin.
Not literally eating, but it's a direct sort of bodily benefit of
consumption. Eating oil, drinking oil is not eating. It's not something that
actually gives you benefit. It's like you damage the oil. If I
damage the כהן's Kohen property, I pay him back for the principal,
but it's not like I actually ate it because it's not a
process of really deriving benefit. Okay, so therefore it's clear that when
you directly drink oil we cannot consider it a normal process of
benefit.
Wait, but if you put it
in the salad then you'd eat it? We're getting there, we're getting
there. So therefore you would not pay, and therefore it would not
be in the category of כי יאכל. ki yochal. So that can't
be the case of giving it a ברכה. bracha. And which would
raise the question in general, let's say a person did for some
reason directly drink oil. Would they make any ברכה? bracha? Would they
make שהכל? shehakol? So this now we're going to enter into this
area where when something doesn't get its primary ברכה bracha because it's
not, you're not getting a normal benefit, it's not in its natural
form, how does it get demoted? Does it get demoted to sort
of a שהכל shehakol level, or does it get demoted to no
ברכה bracha at all? Maybe it gets demoted from a בורא פרי
העץ borei pri ha'eitz to a בורא פרי האדמה. borei pri ha'adama.
Okay, so this is going to be a whole question of degrees
of change and degrees of difference of it from its sort of
natural בורא פרי העץ borei pri ha'eitz state, what ברכה bracha now
takes its place?
You jumped all the way to מזיק.
mazeik. Well exactly, if it's מזיק, mazeik, you would think you don't
make any ברכה. bracha. Right. So let's see where the גמרא Gemara
says. אלא דקאכיל ליה על ידי פת. Ela dekachil lei al yedei
pat.
So fine, you're eating it by dipping your bread into it. So
the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי, ei hachi, if that's true, הוי
ליה פת עיקר והוא טפלה. havei lei pat ikar vehu tfeila. You're
still not making a ברכה bracha on it. The פת pat is
the core and the oil is the secondary. ותנן, Utnan, and we
taught in the משנה, Mishna, זה הכלל, zeh haklal, this is the
principle, כל שהוא עיקר ועמו טפלה, kol shehu ikar ve'imo tfeila, anything
that one thing is the primary, the other thing is the secondary,
מברך על העיקר ופוטר את הטפלה, mevarech al ha'ikar upoteir et hatfeila,
you make the ברכה bracha on the primary and you exempt the
secondary item. So you wouldn't make a ברכה bracha on oil if
you're dipping your bread into it. You know, that could be a
good argument like even if you're dipping your cracker into it, by
bread you... There's a better reason, if your bread and המוציא Hamotzi
it covers everything. Okay, but anyway, so if you're dipping something into
it, it would always be secondary. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא
דקשתי ליה על ידי אניגרון. ela d’kashati lei al yedei anigron.
You're drinking it in some type of a mixture, this אניגרון anigron
mixture. We'll see in a minute what this is, I mean basically
it's a type of oil and different types of spices and other
types of food that are picked, put in. So it's some type
of a mixture of oil, it's a, right, it's a drink that's
a mixture of oil and other things. So Gazpacho? Maybe, I don't
know. דאמר רבה בר שמואל de-amar Rabba bar Shmuel אניגרון מיא דסילקי,
anigron maya de-silki, אניגרון anigron is water of a beets. So presumably
it was some type of a beet borscht that was mixed into
it or you know beet, well it seems like it was more
liquid than solid. It was mixed into it oil.
אסיגרון asigron which is some other type of a drink מיא דכולהו
שלקי maya de-kulu shalki is water from other types of boiled vegetables.
Anyway, you would have these various types of liquids that would be
drunk that you would have olive oil mixed into it. It's like
people have this health drink, right? What do they do? They like
blend raw eggs together with other types of stuff. So okay, you
wouldn't drink the raw egg by themselves, but maybe in some type
of a blend you would. And therefore maybe the olive oil maybe
is the primary, you wouldn't drink it by itself but in this
blended drink you drink it. And therefore according to this, that would
be the case you make בורא פרי העץ. borei pri ha'etz. So
now the גמרא Gemara says, top of ל"ו עמוד א', lamed vav
amud aleph, אם כן הוי ליה אניגרון עיקר ושמן טפל. im ken
havi lei anigron ikkar ve-shemen tafel. No, that's not true. In that
type of a blended drink, the beet juice is what is primary,
the oil is secondary. And we go back to the principle ותנן
זה הכלל כל שהוא עיקר ועמו טפלה מברך על העיקר ופוטר את
הטפלה, v'tenan zeh haklal kol shehu ikkar v'imo tafelah mevarech al ha'ikkar
u'poter et hatafelah, that you make the primary, you make the ברכה
beracha on the primary, on the beet juice. גמרא Gemara says הכא
במאי עסקינן בחושש בגרונו. hacha be-mai askinan be-choshesh bigrono. We're talking now
that you've got a sore throat and you're drinking olive oil in
order to because somehow that's helpful for your sore throat.
Yes, so if you have
an
olive oil tasting, right, you actually are primarily interested in the taste
of the dip. So the answer could very well be yes, but
the גמרא Gemara maybe didn't consider that as a normal possibility. The
interesting question is going to be when it gets to מזונות mezonot
and bread because again, jumping a little bit ahead, the משנה mishna
that speaks about עיקר וטפל ikkar ve-tafel talks about in the context
of bread. And actually, the משנה mishna there even talks about the
idea if you're having herring and you're having bread, you know, in
order because it's too salty or whatever, the herring is really the
עיקר. ikkar. But what the הלכה halacha does develop that even though
bread does not seem to have any particular status that there could
be a context in which bread is טפל tafel and מזונות mezonot
is טפל, tafel, there's another whole sort of push in the גמרא
Gemara that when bread and מזונות mezonot are on the scene, everything
else pales. Okay, so we'll leave it an open question, but in
theory, the possible answer is definitely possibly yes. Okay, if you were
dipping other things into it, I don't know, cucumbers into it, then
you would definitely, then definitely the answer would be yes. But when
it's bread and מזונות, mezonot, there are other possibilities. So now you
say you have, so now the גמרא Gemara says, you've got a
sore throat and you're drinking olive oil to help your throat and
that would make it, it's not damaging, it's healthy for you and
therefore you're going to make a בורא פרי העץ. borei pri ha'etz.
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says with this.
דתניא הכי תניא דברייתא, de-tanya hachi tenya de-braisa, חושש בגרונו, choshesh bigrono,
if somebody has a sore throat on שבת, Shabbos, and שבת Shabbos
you're not allowed to do certain things for you know for רפואה,
refuah, for curative things. So before anybody gets upset about that, let's
defer that to when we get to שבת. Shabbos. Okay, לא יערענו
בשמן תחילה בשבת. lo ye-ar-enu be-shemen techila be-shabbos. Do not gargle with
oil on שבת. Shabbos. That's a clear act of רפואה, refuah, of
something curative. אבל נותן שמן הרבה לתוך אניגרון ובולע. aval noten shemen
harbe le-toch anigron u-vole'a. But you could have an אניגרון anigron mix,
which is a normal thing people drink, so it's not obviously done
for רפואה, refuah, but it could have a high oil content, much
higher than normal, and you swallow it and then it looks like
the, it's as if you're doing an act of eating but it
has a side benefit of a curative process. So that's allowed on
שבת. Shabbos. But what you see is that there are times where
you can have an אניגרון anigron mix that the oil is the
עיקר ikkar and is maybe the majority of it when you have
a sore throat, and that would be a case in which you
would make a בורא פרי העץ. borei pri ha'etz. So now the
גמרא Gemara says פשיטא. pshita. Okay, if that's the case it's obvious.
So you're drinking olive oil in a very particular context where that
is normal to do and that is the עיקר. ikkar. So of
course you'll make a בורא פרי העץ. borei pri ha'etz. Now if
you ask me, it's not פשיטא pshita because as I said, maybe
only when something is in its natural form, but the משנה mishna
assumes not that way because משנה mishna says you make a בורא
פרי העץ borei pri ha'etz on everything except wine, which assumes that
other types of things that have changed form, you would keep the
ברכה. beracha. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, so if it's a
changed form, maybe it's obvious you keep the ברכה beracha and there
it should be obvious you make a בורא פרי העץ. borei pri
ha'etz. So what does the גמרא Gemara say? No. מהו דתימא אימא,
mah d'teima eima, I might have thought כיון דלרפואה קא מיכוין, keivan
de-li-refuah ka-michaven, since you're doing it for the purpose of רפואה, refuah,
לא ליברך עליה כלל, lo livarech alei klal, don't make any ברכה.
beracha. It's no longer food, it's medicine. קא משמע לן כיון דאית
ליה הנאה מיניה בעי ברוכי. ka-mashma lan keivan de-it lei hana'ah minei
ba'i beruchi. You see that since you get some benefit from it,
you still have to make
a
ברכה. beracha. No, there are cases where—no, they're not saying look at
it differently. There are cases where, when you're drinking אניגרון anigron for
רפואה, refuah, your primary interest is the oil. And I think the
גמרא Gemara is actually implicitly going—saying more, saying that you've actually added
more oil. Right. Right. But there are possibilities as I said before,
which what is עיקר, ikkar, what is טפל tafel depends on you.
Okay? So, and so there could theoretically be a case when you
didn't add more, but the גמרא's Gemara assuming you added more and
that made it עיקר. ikkar. Now in terms of the issue of
medicine, I'm not going to get into this discussion but I will
just put an asterisk here. The גמרא's Gemara case is you still
drink something which is a food, but you are doing it for
medicinal purpose. Okay? And therefore it says, well since you're still getting
benefit from it and it's still, therefore you still make the normal
ברכה bracha בורא פרי העץ. borei pri ha'etz. Let's say, for example,
you are taking just like a sweet cough syrup. Right? Is it
anytime you get benefit even if it's primarily a medicine, you make
a ברכה bracha because you're still getting some benefit—some pleasure, not benefit,
you're always getting benefit because it's a medicine, but physical pleasure, you
make a ברכה? bracha? Or is it only in this case where
the thing is primarily a food—maybe you've changed the proportions a little
bit, but it's still primarily a food with medicinal properties? And your
purpose is medicine, but at least in this case it still remains
primarily a food. So that leaves open the question of making ברכות
brachot on types of like these flavored cough syrups and so on,
which I am not going to answer that but just say it
is an open question.
Right. So according to this then,
forget—so getting back to what we said, if I just wanted to
drink שמן
זית—right.
shemen
zayit We don't say בטלה דעתו אצל כל אדם? batla da'ato etzel
kol adam?
It would be בטלה דעתו אצל כל אדם. batla da'ato etzel kol
adam.
No, no, with the אניגרון. anigron. But I guess people actually do
do this?
They would drink an אניגרון anigron mix? Yeah.
But if I just wanted to then drink—drink שמן זית shemen zayit
because I think that it's, you know, medicinal, like you said, the
diet that people do—right. Then it would be בטלה דעתו אצל כל
אדם? batla da'ato etzel kol adam? Yeah, yeah. I mean, first
of all, if you're not getting any physical pleasure, you're just doing
it for medicinal purpose, then certainly you don't make a ברכה. bracha.
The question you want to ask is, let's say סתם stam I
do enjoy eating oil straight. I've got something that—I like drinking oil
straight. There are people that have weird tastes. Okay, then would you
say in that case you certainly wouldn't make a בורא פרי העץ
borei pri ha'etz because you know, clearly בטלה דעתו. batla da'ato. Would
you say when you get pleasure but normal people wouldn't eat it
at all, you say שהכל shehakol or you don't say any ברכה?
bracha? Okay, let's leave that as an open question for now. But
you certainly would not make a בורא פרי העץ. borei pri ha'etz.
Yes.
What's the קא משמע לן ka mashma lan here? Is it that
it doesn't matter what the כוונה kavana is?
That as long—it seems—the minimal קא משמע לן ka mashma lan is
if you're eating something that's a food and you're getting pleasure from
it, then your כוונה kavana for treating it as medicine does not
change the ברכה. bracha. Okay, that's the קא משמע לן. ka mashma
lan. I didn't say this is a food, though.
It just says—I—I know.
I said the minimal קא משמע לן. ka mashma lan. You could
make a—try to make a stronger statement, that even if it's not
a food, any medicine that you get benefit from, but I'm just
saying that's not necessarily warranted by the case, by the data. Yes.
Are you suggesting that when we say a ברכה bracha it's because
we get pleasure from bread or from—yes. What if we eat something
we don't get pleasure from? A mother tells a
child—right.
So that's an interesting question of defining pleasure,
because clearly sort of medicinal pleasure is not—is not what's defined, but
the normal pleasure that comes through eating is both taste and filling
you up, right, which is a little bit not immediately sensed, but
it's, you know—but if you're hungry—right. So you're
raising an interesting point. Let's say something's completely bland, no pleasure, but
I eat it to fill me up. Right. Not even that. I
eat it because my parents say so. But yes, but the simple
answer is it's a good question and you know what, we'll see
maybe a little bit about that when we get to water. Because
water is the גמרא Gemara sort of discusses, you know, discusses a
similar type of a case where it's more about sort of quenching
thirst than it is about taste. Okay? So let's leave that as
the—as an open question, what happens when there's no taste but it
has other sort—other food purposes. Okay. Yes.
But a child isn't חייב chayav in a ברכה. bracha.
Well, yes, but let's say it's a thirteen-year-old child. Okay, okay, twelve-year-old.
Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now moving on. Now we
a little bit depart the direct commentary on the משנה Mishnah and
go into a direct discussion of based on these sort of theme
opened in the משנה, Mishnah, of various types of foods that are
either unusual to eat like the oil, or that are changed form
like the wine, like the oil, so let's see where the גמרא
Gemara goes. קימחא דחיטי. kimcha de'chitti. Let's say you have wheat flour,
you're just eating wheat flour straight. So רב יהודה אמר בורא פרי
האדמה. Rav Yehuda amar borei pri ha'adamah. It's בורא פרי האדמה borei
pri ha'adamah the same way—now רשי Rashi makes an important point. He
points us to a later גמרא Gemara that a later משנה Mishnah
that says, a ברייתא, braita, excuse me, that says that if you
chew kernels of wheat, you make a בורא פרי האדמה. borei pri
ha'adamah. Now again, was it nat—maybe it was normal to chew kernels
of wheat. For us we might ask is that completely not a
normal thing and maybe you make a שהכל shehakol or whatever, but
the גמרא Gemara says if you chew kernels of wheat you make
a בורא פרי האדמה. borei pri ha'adamah. So now what happens when
those... kernels are not in their normal form, they're in a flour
form. Would you keep the בורא פרי האדמה Borei Pri Ha'adamah ברכה
Beracha in this changed form? So let's take a look.
So, רב יהודה אמר בורא פרי האדמה, Rav Yehuda amar Borei Pri
Ha'adamah, you still say a בורא פרי האדמה. Borei Pri Ha'adamah.
Natural and not processed or normal be in the way people normally...
No, thank you, I didn't mean... I meant natural. Okay, thank you.
I mean, well actually we're going to clarify this as we go.
But for now let's assume natural. Okay, when you chew the wheat
in its natural unprocessed form it's בורא פרי האדמה. Borei Pri Ha'adamah.
Once it's processed and changed and it's in flour, would you keep
the ברכה? Beracha? So let's take a look. So, רב יהודה אמר
בורא פרי האדמה. Rav Yehuda amar Borei Pri Ha'adamah. רב נחמן אמר
שהכל נהיה בדברו. Rav Nachman amar Shehakol Niheyah Bidvaro. You say okay,
so it's a debate. So I'm clearly you're saying some ברכה Beracha
you're getting benefit from it, but do you keep the ברכה Beracha
as you do when it's in its natural form? אמר ליה רבא
לרב נחמן, Amar lei Rava l'Rav Nachman, so said רבא Rava to
רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, לא תיפלוג עליה דרב יהודה, Lo tiflog alei
d'Rav Yehuda, don't argue on רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, דרבי יוחנן ושמואל
קיימי כוותיה, d'Rabbi Yochanan u'Shmuel kaymi k'vatei, that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
and שמואל Shmuel say like what רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said, which
is you keep the בורא פרי האדמה Borei Pri Ha'adamah ברכה. Beracha.
How do you know? דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, D'amar Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel, because רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said in the name of
שמואל, Shmuel, so this is רב יהודה Rav Yehuda himself knew this
tradition from שמואל, Shmuel, so here he said in the name of
שמואל, Shmuel, וכן אמר רבי יצחק אמר רבי יוחנן v'chen amar Rabbi
Yitzchak amar Rabbi Yochanan and similarly רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said, שמן
זית, Shemen zayit, olive oil, מברכין עליו בורא פרי העץ. mevarchin alav
Borei Pri Ha'etz. Didn't we just get through a whole discussion before
that said that you make a בורא פרי העץ Borei Pri Ha'etz
in a case where olive oil is a normal thing to eat?
So you see even though it's in a changed form, it retains
the ברכה. Beracha. So you see אלמא אף על גב דאשתני, Alma
af al gav d'ishtani, even though it's in a non-natural form, במילתיה
קאי, b'miltei kai, it retains its original status and its original ברכה.
Beracha. הכא נמי, Hacha nami, here too, אף על גב דאשתני, af
al gav d'ishtani, although it changed, במילתיה קאי, b'miltei kai, it retains
its original status. So you keep the ברכה. Beracha. גמרא Gemara says
מי דמי? Mi dami? One minute, you can't compare those cases. How's
that comparable? התם לית ליה עילויא אחרינא, Hatam leit lei iluya achrina,
there by the olive oil there's no further state of higher state
that it can reach. הכא אית ליה עילויא אחרינא בפת, Hacha it
lei iluya achrina b'pat, flour has a higher state to reach. It
can become bread. Now according to this, what undermines its status as
flour is that it is going to... it could become bread. Now
according to this, what undermines its status as flour is that it
is going to... it could become bread. If it has some higher
potential. You could have reframed that and said forget higher potential, this
is just not a good normal state that people eat this thing
in. Maybe they chew wheat, maybe they eat bread, but they don't
directly eat flour. Okay, so it's a little funny that the גמרא
Gemara emphasizes the problem here is that it's in its process to
becoming bread when maybe part of the problem is that this is
not a normal way of, you know, this is not seen as
a good state of the thing itself. A good state of... I
mean it's not just not normal to eat it because it's not
normal to eat olive oil. But the point is what's a good
state when you're dealing with olives? So one good state is olives,
one good state is, you know, ready for consumption, one is olives,
one is olive oil. What's a good state of consumption for wheat?
Well if you chew kernels, that's true, bread is another thing. But
flour is not in its state of fit for consumption, okay, which
could basically be what the גמרא Gemara means. That it's in an
intermediate state, not food. I mean it's not yet food. It's not
in a state yet where it's fit for consumption and therefore you
don't make... alright so you get some somewhat... but it's not yet
in its state where it's primarily fit for consumption and therefore it
does not retain the ברכה. Beracha. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. והיכא דאית ליה עילויא אחרינא לא מברכינן עליה בורא פרי
האדמה? V'heicha d'it lei iluya achrina lo mevarchinan alei Borei Pri Ha'adamah?
So are you telling me that if something has a higher state
to reach, it's in an intermediate state, you would not get the
בורא פרי האדמה, Borei Pri Ha'adamah, אלא שהכל? ela Shehakol? You don't
get שהכל, Shehakol, that's what you're telling me here? Flour only gets
שהכל Shehakol because it's in this intermediate state. והאמר רבי זירא אמר
רב מתנא אמר שמואל, V'ha'amar Rabbi Zeira amar Rav Mattana amar Shmuel,
did רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira say in the name of רב מתנא
Rav Mattana in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, אקרא חייא, akra chaya,
a raw gourd, וקמחא דשערי, v'kimcha d'sa'ari, and barley flour, מברכין עליו
שהכל נהיה בדברו. mevarchin alav Shehakol Niheyah Bidvaro.
You say שהכל. Shehakol. Why? Because they're not fit for consumption. Okay,
now notice by the way, here's the case David where you have
a natural state, a raw gourd, but it's not yet fit for
consumption, that also knocks it down to a שהכל. Shehakol. So here
you have two things that are not fit for consumption, they get
a שהכל. Shehakol. What does that prove? מאי לאו, Mai lav, but
he said barley flour. Barley flour, barley anyway is more animal food
than human food and so on. So he says מאי לאו דחיטי,
Mai lav d'chiti, so too is wheat flour you would say בורא
פרי האדמה. Borei Pri Ha'adamah. It specifically said barley flour. He says
לא, Lo, no, not necessarily. דחיטי נמי שהכל נהיה בדברו, D'chiti nami
Shehakol Niheyah Bidvaro, you would also say שהכל Shehakol on wheat flour.
Why? ולשמעינן דחיטי וכל שכן דשערי, v'lishmeinan d'chiti v'chol shekein d'sa'ari, so
tell us then wheat flour and don't bother telling us barley flour.
No. אי אשמעינן דחיטי, Ei ashmeinan d'chiti, if it told us wheat
flour, הוה אמינא הני מילי דחיטי, hava amina hanei milei d'chiti, fine
wheat flour gets a
שהכל. Shehakol. אבל דשערי, Aval d'sa'ari, but barley flour, לא נברך עליה
כלל, lo nevareich alei klal, doesn't get any ברכה Beracha because maybe
it's completely not something that normal people do, no benefit. קא משמע
לן Ka mashma lan that it does get some ברכה. Beracha. So
now we're going to get... I'll step back and I'll wrap this
up, but now we're sort of at the very bottom line. At
what stage is something so not inedible, not really inedible, but so
not a normal thing to eat, that it gets no ברכה? Berakhah?
So now the גמרא Gemara is saying I might have thought that
that would be the case. And now the גמרא Gemara is going
to ask, what is the bottom floor? So the גמרא Gemara says
ומי גרע ממלח וזומס? Umi gara mi-melach ve-zumes?
One minute, how could I have thought that barley flour would be
worse than salt or זומס? zumes? The question what זומס zumes is,
רש"י Rashi says it means a type of a salt water or
brine, excuse me, or something of that nature. And דתניא, de-tanya, we
taught in the משנה, Mishnah, or actually דתניא, de-tanya, ברייתא, Baraita, על
המלח ועל הזומס אומר שהכל נהיה בדברו. Al ha-melach ve-al ha-zumes omer
she-hakol nihyeh bi-devaro. You say שהכל Shehakol on salt and brine and
salt water, even things that obviously normal people don't eat, so it
seems like everything is going to get a שהכל. Shehakol. How could
I have thought that barley is worse, barley flour is worse? So
the גמרא Gemara says אצטריך, Itzterikh, no you need to tell me
that. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka daitakh amina, I would have thought מלח
וזומס עבידי אינשי דשדי לפומייהו. Melach ve-zumes avidi inshi de-shadi le-pumeihu. People
do sometimes throw a little, put a little salt in their
mouths, definitely people that have a real, like, I can speak personally,
that have a little bit of an addiction to salt, so sometimes
you have a little salt craving, you put a little salt in
your mouth. People would do that. So it gets a שהכל. Shehakol.
אבל קמחא דשערי, Aval kimcha de-sa'arei, but barley flour, טחול וקשי לקוקיאני,
tehol ve-kashi le-kukiani,
since barley flour actually causes, according to some, like
intestinal worms, it actually is hurtful to your health, לא לברכי עליה
כלל, lo livarkhei alei klal, you shouldn't make a ברכה Berakhah at
all because maybe that's really not considered a food. קמשמע לן כיון
דאית ליה הנאה מיניה בעי ברוכי, Kamashma lan keivan de-it lei hana'ah
mineih ba'ei brukhi, no, since in the end people will put it
in their mouth and they like the taste even though it causes
them some bad effects, nevertheless בעי ברוכי, ba'ei brukhi, you make a
ברכה. Berakhah. So according to this, you know, let's take, sit, take
a moment just to say what we have said. In terms of
are there things you make no ברכה Berakhah on, it seems like
as long as you're getting some type of pleasure and benefit, you
still make a ברכה. Berakhah. Now again, the question is, let's say
you combine,
the גמרא Gemara sounds like some people do it, it's sort of
acknowledged as an acceptable type of a thing. Will it get to
a stage where you're considered totally crazy to do this and therefore
gets no ברכה, Berakhah, that we haven't yet explored? But as long
as this is a type of thing that some people will do
and there's some degree of benefit, you will actually make a ברכה,
Berakhah, you will retain a שהכל Shehakol even if it's not such
a normal thing to be doing as long as it's not totally
crazy. That at least minimally we can say from this גמרא. Gemara.
What if the whole benefit is sort of filling you and not
taste? We're bracketing that. Now in terms of the question about changed
form, the other thing we've learned is, very another important principles, that
even if something is in its natural form, if it's not yet
edible, right, what do you make? You make not only not would
it go down from a בורא פרי העץ Borei Peri Ha'etz to
a בורא פרי האדמה, Borei Peri Ha'adamah, it goes straight down to
שהכל. Shehakol. Okay, if you're doing something, you're eating raw gourd, okay,
so presumably again we have to assume that you're getting some benefit
and it's not a crazy thing to do, right, so at least
you go to a שהכל. Shehakol. But the point is, even in
its natural form that doesn't save it. Once something is not some—is,
you know, not the sort of the normal way of deriving benefit,
you don't make its classic ברכה. Berakhah. As long as you're getting
some benefit, you make שהכל, Shehakol, but if it's not the normal
way of deriving benefit, you're not, you're not making its classic ברכה.
Berakhah. That's what we learned from the gourd. Raw gourd, even natural
form, you make שהכל. Shehakol. The flip, let's say it's not in
its natural form but it is a natural way of deriving benefit,
okay, like olive oil,
or even let's whatever, how natural it is, olive oil, well let's
do the olive oil. Olive oil case, there you would say a
בורא פרי העץ. Borei Peri Ha'etz. Okay, so you've sort of got
this, basically what we're seeing now is so far natural form doesn't
matter. You have one case where it's natural form and not a
normal way of deriving benefit, there is some benefit, שהכל, Shehakol, that's
the gourd. On the other case, not its natural form but it
is the normal way of deriving benefit, that's the olive oil, when
you have the case of the olive oil with the mixture, that's
בורא פרי העץ. Borei Peri Ha'etz. So you don't need it to
be in its natural form and it doesn't save it either. The
key question right now at this stage is, is it a normal
way of deriving benefit? The only type of thing the גמרא Gemara
excluded was, or debated, was the wheat flour because the wheat flour
is has—is—is a type of of an issue there where the גמרא
Gemara is saying that that might be a בורא פרי האדמה Borei
Peri Ha'adamah because that is again not really in its sort of
final and ideal form. So that is going to become a question
about
השתני לעילויא. Ishtani le-illuya. When something has a combination of change in
form and it's not really in its ideal stage right now, and
that that makes it lose a ברכה Berakhah and goes from the
בורא פרי האדמה Borei Peri Ha'adamah to the שהכל. Shehakol.
You have a good question. So even though it says כיון דאית
ליה הנאה מיניה בעי ברוכי, Keivan de-it lei hana'ah mineih ba'ei brukhi,
is this because it's a food? You're saying minimally that's implicit in
there. Because it's a food, you know, abstractly, and I get the
הנאה. hana'ah. Right, versus let's say I decided to flavor some sawdust
and eat it.
Right. Yeah, yeah, yeah. So we're assuming these things are foods and
that's part of it. Okay, so I hope that's pretty clear. Look,
it's not going to be totally clear because there's a lot of
debates about these things and that's why people kids study. for a
year for ברכות. brachos. But anyway, or they just memorize lists more
than they memorize rules. But anyway, but the basic point here is
that we've seen is as I've said, something can be in its
natural form and still get a שהכל, shehakol, something could be in
its changed form and still get the original ברכה bracha בורא פרי
העץ, borei pri ha'etz, and the wheat flour presents an interesting middle
case where it's not natural,
and it... but because it's also not in a good form, that
also lowers it down. The combination of being אשתני לגריעותא ishtani li'greiusa
lowers it down to שהכל. shehakol. Okay, so let's see where this
continues.
Even barley flour, as if to say קמשמע לן, kamashma lan, we
would have only thought...
Right. Now I will tell you for example that if you think
about let's think about a practical example for us, let's talk about
apple juice or orange juice. Okay. So for many people, right, they
don't like apples or oranges, but they'll... or I don't know, whatever,
but they really would prefer orange juice to eating an orange. Okay.
So that would be like maybe an אשתני לעילויא, ishtani li'ilyusa, you
know, a positive change or at least same level. Orange juice... orange
juice is not really like going down to flour, right, where it's
just in some intermediate stage. This is like an ideal stage of
consumption, so maybe you should make a בורא פרי העץ, borei pri
ha'etz, right, that would be... certainly should be worse than somebody who's
going to drink olive oil. Okay, so that should sort of be
a natural sort of, you know, derivation from what we have just
learned. If, however, you had something that was let's say a derivative
and more of an ingredient than something that you would eat directly.
What would be a good example about that?
Cream... I don't know, I guess... not the cream is a cocoa...
like a cocoa bean? Like if you just had cocoa. Who would
eat just cocoa?
Right, right. According to this, right, an herb, like some type of
a... yeah, like let's say vanilla extract or something like that, you
know, or something of that nature. Anyway, something that you would use
as an ingredient, right, but not directly, then according to this if
somebody wanted to eat it, like lemon juice. Okay, lemon juice. That's
a good example. People buy lemon juice in the store obviously, that's
something that people want and desire, but you don't drink lemon juice
directly. You use that as an ingredient in something else. So if
you're going to drink lemon juice, you would make a שהכל shehakol
according to this. That's אשתני לגריעותא. ishtani li'greiusa. Okay, it's both changed
and it's not in its ideal form. Yes. What about... what's that?
Tomato juice? Do you make a העץ ha'etz on orange juice is
the question. So I'm going to get to that. We'll get... but
at least what we've seen so far, the answer should be yes.
Right, applesauce should be the same question. Right. As the juice, as
orange juice, apple juice, applesauce, doesn't matter what the form is, it's
the same. Exactly.
Exactly. Now to qualify all of that, I will... let me draw
your attention to תוספות tosafos of קמחא דחטי. kimcha de'chitti. תוספות tosafos
about the wheat flour. תוספות tosafos says the following: נראה דלא מיירי
בקמחא ממש, nireh d'lo mairi b'kimcha mamash, we're not talking about total
real flour, full... fully turned into flour. דאם כן לא שייכא ביה
ברכה דבורא פרי האדמה, de'im kein lo shaycha bei bracha d'borei pri
ha'adama, you would never make a בורא פרי האדמה borei pri ha'adama
if it just looked like flour. תוספות tosafos assumes to retain the
ברכה bracha it has to still have some quality of the original
natural state. Okay. אלא מיירי בקמח שקורין ella mairi b'kemach she'korin whatever
איסקלאר iskalayar I don't know או בקמח שעשו משבולת שועל שמיבשין בתנור,
o be'kemach she'asahu mishibolet shual she'meyabshin b'tanur,
it's some type of a flour that still is a more grainier
flour and it's not total powder and presumably has some of the
original form. So this becomes a question of how processed will something
be or totally lose its original form and can it still retain
the ברכה. bracha. For example, potato chips. When I was... when I
was growing up, you know, I was told, well, normal potato chips
you make a בורא פרי האדמה. borei pri ha'adama. Pringles you make
a שהכל. shehakol. Because Pringles they total turn it into flour and
it's totally loses its original form and they reshape it. So when
it completely loses its original form, then you don't make the original
ברכה bracha at all. Now you have to ask, okay, how about
olive oil? That's just... but you know, what makes olive oil, it
doesn't look any more like the olive, but somehow it's not seen
as not as processed as much. It's not so much that it
has to be visible, you know, the original state, you don't have
to see an olive in the olive oil, but somehow it's more
natural, it's less processed. At what stage of processing breaks something off
from its original and then it becomes, you know, turns into a
שהכל. shehakol. So תוספות tosafos says by flour, to me I don't
really see the big difference between like, you know, highly sifted flour
and and olive oil, like, you know, it's it's, you know, it's
not like it's really changed, it's just pounded and sifted, it's not
like you've, you know, like you've completely transformed it.
Yeah, but the thing is olive oil you can immediately put on
bread. Right.
Flour you can't. No, no, I know, I know, but I'm saying
even without that difference, the
point the גמרא gemara made, but תוספות tosafos is adding this other
this other criteria, yeah.
I was going to say I think in those times they didn't
eat olives.
Right, it was primarily... so we're going to get to that, when...
right, so we're going to get to that, maybe olive oil is
primarily because it's what it's... because even the natural state is not
the ideal state. So we're going to get to that in a
minute. But I just for now I want to just note that
in addition to these issues of... this is the big question... when
something changes form, does it retain the ברכה? bracha? The first qualification
we had is not if it's in an intermediate form and not
an ideal form of consumption. So flour, lemon juice, and so on.
But Tosafot adds also, not if it's been so highly processed. Okay,
whatever that means and exactly how you define it, Tosafot says at
a certain stage of processing it becomes שהכל. shehakol. Okay, so let's
keep on going. Gemara says like this: קורא. kora. Rav Yehuda. קורא.
kora. Now how about קורא, kora, which is not קרא kara which
is a gourd, but this is a קורא kora which is, Rashi
says it's basically hearts of palm. Okay, so Rav Yehuda says בורא
פרי האדמה. borei pri ha'adama. You make בורא פרי האדמה. borei pri
ha'adama. בורא פרי האדמה. borei pri ha'adama. And Shmuel
says שהכל נהיה בדברו. shehakol nihiyah bidvaro. You make a שהכל. shehakol.
So Rav Yehuda says בורא פרי האדמה, borei pri ha'adama, you make
בורא פרי האדמה, borei pri ha'adama, פירא הוא. peira hu. It's a
type of a fruit in a sense that it comes from, you
know, a palm tree. Now if it comes from a palm tree,
why don't you make בורא פרי העץ? borei pri ha'etz? So it's
not a full fruit, it's not the real fruit of the palm,
okay, but it is still something that is growing from the ground.
Right, and therefore you make, exactly, and therefore you make בורא פרי
האדמה. borei pri ha'adama. Okay.
And Shmuel says שהכל נהיה בדברו. shehakol nihiyah bidvaro. הוה סופו להקשות.
hava sofo lehakshot. That if you do not do anything with the
heart of palm, it would turn hard and become part of the
palm itself, and therefore, I mean this part of the palm, but
it would become like a, you know, it would become part like
a palm leaf. And therefore Rashi says it is the tip of
a leaf of the leaves. But from what I understand, hearts of
palm are the actual tip of the entire tree. You take the
heart of
palm, you kill the tree.
I know. So I never understood how we can buy a hearts
of palm in a little thing in the supermarket for two dollars
and keep twenty palms going to get that. Anyway, but so I
don't know if it's a hearts of palm, Rashi says it's the
tip of a leaf. As the leaves grow, the new part of
the leaf is edible, and but as it continues to grow it
becomes harder and inedible. That's what Rashi says. Not exactly hearts of
palm. So anyway, Shmuel says that since it's going to get hard
and inedible, you don't give it the בורא פרי האדמה borei pri
ha'adama ברכה. bracha. So now אמר ליה שמואל לרב יהודה, amar leih
Shmuel l'Rav Yehuda, so Shmuel said to Rav Yehuda, שיננא, shinana, which
is like sharp one or some of the גאונים geonim say that
שיננא shinana comes from the word שן, shen, tooth, that Rav Yehuda
had like long teeth. I don't know. Anyway, but normally Rashi interprets
it as sharp one. Sharp one, כוותך מסתברא, kevatach mistabra, actually your
position makes more sense than mine, that you say a בורא פרי
האדמה. borei pri ha'adama. Why? דהא פוגלא, deha pugla, a radish, סופו
להקשות, sofo lehakshot, is going to, if you leave a radish in
the ground, it will become hard and
inedible, ומברכינן עליה בורא פרי האדמה, umvarchinan aleih borei pri ha'adama, but
if you eat it in its primary state, you make a בורא
פרי האדמה. borei pri ha'adama. So here too, if you eat it
in its edible state, you should make a בורא פרי האדמה. borei
pri ha'adama. Your position actually makes more sense. But the Gemara says
ולא היא. velo hi. But you know what? It's not a good
comparison.
But the Gemara says ולא היא.
velo hi. פוגלא, pugla, a radish, אדעתא דפוגלא נטעי אינשי. ada'ata depugla
natei inshi. Here's the point
that was just made, that a radish is planted for the intention
of eating it in this sort of soft stage when it's edible.
דיקלא, dikla, when you plant a palm tree,
לא אדעתא דקורא נטעי אינשי. lo ada'ata dekora natei inshi. You're not
planting a palm tree so you can get this like leaf tips
of the leaf. So it's not the purpose for which it's planted.
And now we get this interesting question: Do you make the ברכה
bracha when something was not planted for that purpose? Okay, it's a
benefit that you get from it, but it was not planted for
that purpose. This year is even saying in its natural state. Okay,
so if, you know, Paula's point could be, let's say you plant
olive trees but nobody's going to eat the olives, they're just going
to eat the olive oil, would you make a בורא פרי העץ
borei pri ha'etz on the olives themselves even?
But you could also say, so that's one question in the natural
state. You can even strengthen the question if it's in a changed
state and it's not the way in which the purpose for which
it was planted. So let's see where the Gemara goes with this.
וכל היכא דלא נטעי אינשי אדעתא דהכי לא מברכינן עליה? vechol heicha
dela natei inshi ada'ata dehachi la mvarchinan aleih? You mean to tell
me anytime the thing isn't planted for that you don't make the
normal ברכה? bracha?
והרי צלף, veherei tzalaf, what about צלף tzalaf which is a caper
bush? And this I gotta tell you that what's-his-name, if you, you
know, this is where Steinsaltz is fabulous because he's got these pictures
are great about
this. What page you on? 245?
Yeah, 245 it has the whole bush and the flowers.
Okay, go ahead, go ahead. Okay, so here's a caper bush. Okay,
we're going to see about the various parts of the caper bush.
In it, caper bush people use the fruit of the caper bush,
which looks like this, the caper, and apparently there are buds also
that grow right at the flowers that open into the flowers, and
these buds...
what are these, flowers and then the fruit?
Yeah, there's leaves, there's flowers, there's buds which turn into the flowers,
and there's the fruit. Okay, so how about a caper bush? It
says that what, where are we?
והרי צלף דנטעי אינשי אדעתא דפרחא. veherei tzalaf denatei inshi ada'ata deparcha.
The caper bush is planted with the intent of the פרחא parcha
which sounds like flower, but anyway, but Rashi says and it's interpreted
to mean the actual fruit itself. It's planted for the, because most,
why do people plant their caper bush? They want the fruit.
ותנן, vetnan, nevertheless we learned in the
משנה, mishna, על מיני נצפה al minei nitzpa on
various... the buds on the leaves, the little berries on the leaves,
and that's not the caper. Right. אומר בורא פרי האדמה. Omer borei
pri hadama. You say בורא פרי האדמה. borei pri hadama. ועל האביונות
Ve'al ha'evyonot on the actual fruit itself, which is called the אביונות,
evyonot, ועל הקפריסין. ve'al hakaphrisin. And what are קפריסין? kaphrisin? רש"י Rashi
says קפריסין kaphrisin means the shell, some type of a shell around
the fruit, some type of a covering grows around the fruit. And
because it's going to be very clear from the continued גמרא Gemara
that that is going to be compared to other cases of shells
around things and things that protect the fruit. I have to tell
you שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz says, and he quotes the Greek or whatever,
that this refers to these buds that turn into flowers. So I
looked further when the גמרא Gemara has a whole discussion about how
this קפריסין kaphrisin protects the fruit, he doesn't make any comment on
it. So I don't know how he assumes it's a bud that
becomes a flower and then deal with the later גמרא Gemara that
it says it protects the fruit. But anyway, רש"י Rashi therefore, רש"י
Rashi says we're talking about the actual shell, some type of a
shell around the fruit. Which we've seen is edible. Okay. That's edible.
Right. Oh yeah, exactly. Okay. So, so when it comes to the
fruit itself, ועל הקפריסין ve'al hakaphrisin and the קפריסין, kaphrisin, which again
means let's say for רש"י Rashi a shell around the fruit, these
are things that are normally eaten, אומר בורא פרי העץ. omer borei
pri ha'etz. You say בורא פרי העץ. borei pri ha'etz. What's the
פשט? pshat? The thing that you normally plant the tree for says
בורא פרי העץ. borei pri ha'etz. Other things you get from the
tree, you say בורא פרי האדמה. borei pri hadama. It's not בורא
פרי העץ, borei pri ha'etz, you say בורא פרי האדמה. borei pri
hadama. So it should be exactly the same by the tips of
the leaves by the palm tree. Why do you ex-, how can
you say שהכל? shehakol?
But I don't get it. The whole thing is a bush. Why
isn't the whole thing אדמה? adama? It's not a tree.
So bush, the basic difference is, and there's some, and why do
they make an אדמה adama on bananas and not a בורא פרי
העץ? borei pri ha'etz? So the one thing you have to know
going in is that the definition of tree for halakhic purposes is
something where the thing stays from year to year. So if you
have a bush that doesn't die but stays from year to year,
you make a בורא פרי העץ, borei pri ha'etz, which is why
a lot of berries you say בורא פרי העץ. borei pri ha'etz.
Okay. They're bushes that stay from year to year. A banana tree,
however, the whole tree dies actually and regrows. Yeah. So that's why
a banana tree, even though it's a tree, goes all the way
up there, you still say a בורא פרי האדמה borei pri hadama
not a בורא פרי
העץ.
borei
pri ha'etz.
Because it's a bush that doesn't last from year to year.
Year to year. Okay. So you say בורא פרי העץ. borei pri
ha'etz. Anyway, so what do we see? We see that by-products of
a tree that are not done for the purpose as the primary
benefit, you still make a בורא פרי האדמה. borei pri hadama. So
let the tips of the palm leaves be the same. So the
גמרא Gemara says,
אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, צלף, tzalaph,
by צלף tzalaph נטעי אינש אדעתא דשותא. natei insh ada'ata deshusha. No,
no, no. People actually do plant it for the sake of the
שותא, shusha, which basically means the leaves and all these other things.
You know, there's a primary product, a secondary product, but still when
you're planting the צלף tzalaph tree, you're saying okay great, you know,
I'll get the fruit and I'll get this other stuff. So it
might not be primary, but it's still part of your intent of
what you hope to harvest from the caper bush tree.
דקלא dikla לא נטעי אינש אדעתא דקורא. lo natei insh ada'ata dekora.
When somebody plants a דקלא dikla palm tree, nobody is, normal person
is thinking, oh great, a palm tree, I'll be able to eat
the tips of the leaves. Okay? So every now and then there
are people that would like it, they'll come and they'll eat it,
but that's not a normal sort of, a normal product of this
thing and therefore it's a שהכל. shehakol. So now the גמרא Gemara
says, אף על גב דקלסיה שמואל לרב יהודה, af al gav dekalsei
Shmuel l'Rav Yehuda, although שמואל Shmuel praised רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, says
your position makes more sense, nevertheless, הלכתא כותיה דשמואל. hilchata kevata deShmuel.
We rule like שמואל. Shmuel. Okay? We rule that it's שהכל shehakol
and that what you planted it for is an important part of
the palm tree. Now there's a nice little מוסר musar message here
too. It sort of reminds one of the debate of בית שמאי
Beit Shammai and בית הלל, Beit Hillel, that the גמרא Gemara says
why do we rule like בית הלל Beit Hillel over בית שמאי?
Beit Shammai? Because it says that בית הלל Beit Hillel were sort
of, you know, humble and they would always teach the position of
בית שמאי Beit Shammai before they taught their own position and so
on. So here, the fact that שמואל Shmuel is willing to sort
of concede the strength of the argument of רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda,
in the end the גמרא Gemara says there are ways to make
distinctions, but you know, that also, you know, it's interesting that ironically
or not so ironically maybe, we wind up ruling like שמואל Shmuel
because שמואל Shmuel really was able to hear the argument from the
other side. Okay, but in the end, end of the day, the
הלכה halacha is that when if you have a product of a
tree that is a normal sort of, let's say a normal type
of thing that is hoped to be harvested, but not the primary
produce, you would say a בורא פרי האדמה. borei pri hadama. If
it's a type of a thing that is that is not that
is not a normal sort of product that normal people are expecting,
you know, when you plant the thing it's not something you hope
to harvest and eat, then you would only say a שהכל. shehakol.
So how much is something the fruit of a tree? There are
three degrees. If it's the primary fruit, it's העץ. ha'etz. If it's
what I'd call a secondary fruit, it's an אדמה. adama. It's not
a בורא פרי העץ, borei pri ha'etz, it still comes from the
ground and it's an אדמה. adama. And if it's a type of
a thing that is really never seen as a fruit of the
tree that just happens to be growing from the tree and some
people will eat it, then it becomes a שהכל. shehakol.
Okay, so I want to understand this. I mean he said that
the קורא kora is the heart of palm, right?
Well Steinmetz said it.
So is that what we make? We make—I mean I don't know
if it's palm—but then—so he's saying the heart of palm—What do you
make
that type of a ברכה? Bracha? שהכל. Shehakol. So I don't know.
I assume if you've got any—my guess—any—anything that you are buying in
the supermarket that
is—is נטע אדעתא דהכי, nata ada'ata dehachi, okay? Because that means that
somebody's in the business of planting this and harvesting it and selling
it to the supermarket. So anything you're buying in the supermarket that
comes from the ground is minimally a בורא פרי האדמה, Borei Pri
Ha'adama, all right? I mean assuming that it's in its somewhat natural
and not processed state. The question would be if you're taking a
walk in the forest and you pick a leaf from a tree,
well that's also not even נטע, nata, that's growing naturally. But still,
would normal people plant it for that? That maybe we can discuss.
But anything in the supermarket is נטע אדעתא דהכי. nata ada'ata dehachi.
So you mean just the ברכה Bracha for something could change? Yeah.
To say once there's a market for something it becomes a matter
of popular perception and cultivation. Right. Well right. That which had been
previously בורא פרי האדמה Borei Pri Ha'adama could become בורא פרי העץ.
Borei Pri Ha'etz.
That's true. That is true. Exactly. Once considered primary. Or שהכל Shehakol
to אדמה. Adama. Or שהכל Shehakol in the case of the palm.
David you want to say something?
There seems like there is a tension here between case law and
abstracting principle. So where—where do the principles really get codified?
Where—where—So that's a very good point. You know, generally the process starts
from case law and the abstraction comes later. Look, you see it
already starting in the תורה Torah where most, you know, of the
laws in משפטים Mishpatim are very specific: כי יגח שור איש את
שור רעהו Ki yigach shor ish et shor re'ehu and so on.
And then it gets abstracted, you know, in the גמרא. Gemara. And
often you see it in the משנה Mishnah because the משנה Mishnah
will say: Here are the case, here is a case, case, case,
this—זה הכלל, zeh haklal, this is the general rule. Which again, you
could say that's a literary point but one gets a sense it
started with the cases coalescing and then the rule was articulated. And
more and more as the time progresses, as the generations get later
in the גמרא Gemara historically, there's more abstraction and more discussion of
sort of rules rather than of cases. But you are correct that
there is this period of tension that you're trying to articulate rules,
you challenge it with cases and it leads to a modification of
the rules. And that's exactly what we're seeing here. So that's an
excellent point.
So Paul was saying earlier that in ancient times—I didn't know this—that
people did not eat olives.
So if that's the case—Oh I didn't even realize for a while
that olives are only eaten after pickling. You can't eat raw olives.
They're horrible. Yeah. Oh.
Okay. That is my question because because I was going to say
if somebody in those days decided, 'Gee, I think I like these
things'
what—what—what blessing would that be? Right. You mean, but I—I—I don't know—is—Paul
are you saying that people didn't cure olives and—and eat them?
That came later.
Curing olives came later. So at the time when they weren't cured
and all you had were olives, there would be no ברכה. Bracha.
Now, I—we'll—we'll end here because I don't want to get—we'll end here
with one final statement though which is this whole question about—I'll just
give you some things to think about which is seriously debated—why don't
we make a בורא פרי העץ Borei Pri Ha'etz on apple juice
and orange juice? Okay, it's השתני, ishtani, but it's not—it's certainly its
גופא gufa or whatever, it's certainly not too heavily processed like the
case of the גמרא. Gemara. It's certainly not in an intermediate stage
and so on. So there are a couple of very serious opinions
to say you do make בורא פרי העץ Borei Pri Ha'etz on
apple juice and orange juice. However, the practice is not. And one
reason is originally in the time of the גמרא Gemara no normal
person would squeeze juice for anything other than olive oil and grapes.
Everything else was eaten—there would be no sense—everything else was considered the
גמרא Gemara said like sort of like a sweat of the fruit
and not seen as a primary product. It was not natural to
eat. So clearly at that time it was השתני לגריעותא ishtani legareiuta
and you'd make a שהכל. Shehakol. Nowadays it's very different. Nowadays they
plant specific types of oranges for the sake of making orange juice
and the whole thing is planted for that purpose. And therefore a
lot of people do argue that nowadays you really should be making
a בורא פרי העץ, Borei Pri Ha'etz, but you know the מנהג
העולם minhag ha'olam is to make a שהכל. Shehakol. It see—it would
seem bizarre on a drink to make a בורא פרי העץ, Borei
Pri Ha'etz, but the גמרא Gemara had it by the olive oil.
There's other questions which I'll leave you to think about which is
coffee beans and cocoa beans. Right? So these are other cases where
even though you mix things with the chocolate, the chocolate is the
עיקר. ikar. People plant the cocoa beans for the sake of the
chocolate. People plant the coffee beans for the sake of coffee although
there, you know, 99 percent is the water, there's a tiny—just flavored
by the coffee. Anyway, there—what? Really? Is it—how about if you have
dark—well, there are the dark 70 percent dark chocolates, those types of
things. Right. It might depend on the proportions. Anyway, there as well
there are those that say you make a בורא פרי העץ. Borei
Pri Ha'etz. And the מנהג העולם minhag ha'olam is to make שהכל.
Shehakol. I will say, you know, more people are prepared to consider
בורא פרי העץ Borei Pri Ha'etz by food than they are by
liquid. But you don't see that in—we associate liquid שהכל. Shehakol. That's
like our association. But you don't see that in the גמרא. Gemara.
This question about change and does it get better and worse and
so on and it doesn't have to be in the natural state.
And these become core principles for ברכות. brachot. חכמים, Chachamim, continue tomorrow.